This is where we left off in the previous video, we used
पिछले वीडियो में यहा पे छोड़ा था, हमने इस्तेमाल किया था
the LEFT and FIND functions
LEFT और FIND कार्य का
to chop off that part of data that we need in order for us to be able
ताकि हम निकाल सके उस डेटा के भाग को जिससे हम
to use the value in calculations. And in the meantime,
उस वॅल्यू का इस्तेमाल कर सकते हैं हिसाब में. और उस दौरान
you, in the exercises, have also added this Trend column,
आपने एक्सर्साइज़स में, एक और ट्रेड कॉलम जोड़ा
where you chop off the first part of the Change column.
जहा पे आपने चेंज कॉलम से पहला भाग निकाला था.
And I'm not going to show you the formula, so if you haven't done the exercises yet
और मैं आपको यहा पे वो फ़ॉर्मूला नई दिखाने वाली हूँ अगर आपने वो एक्सर्साइज़स नही किया है अभी तक
you still have an opportunity to do so. What I've also done in the meantime is: I've
तो आपके पास अभी भी मौका है करने के लिए. इस दौरना मैं जो किया है, वो यह है की: मैने
added not just the value,
नही बस वॅल्यू डाला है,
the number of shares I have, for the first row,
शयर  की संख्या है मेरे पास, पहले रो में
but also for all of the others. So I've just gone back to this first worksheet
बल्कि बाकी रोस के लिए भी. तो अभी मैं फिर से पहले वर्कशीट पे गयी हूँ
and copied all the data in. And as I said in the previous video - yes, I will explain
और छापा है सारे डेटा को. जैसे मैने बताया था पहले वीडियो में, मैं आपको समझौँगी
you a better way
एक बेहतर तरीका से
to connect two worksheets together. If you already know it, don't worry, this is
जिससे आप दो वर्कशीट्स को जोड़ सकते हैं. अगर आप पहले से जानते हैं, तो चिंता की कोई बात नई है, यह
not how I think it's done,
तरीका नई है जो मैने सोचा था,
but for this exercise it's just easier to copy the data in.
पर इस एक्सर्साइज़ के लिए डेटा छापना आसान है.
So this is typically the point, if you have a lot of columns,
आप अभी इस स्थिति में हैं जहा पे आपके पास बहुत सारे कॉलम्स हैं
where you're going to want to clean up your worksheet.
और आप अपने वर्कशीट को सॉफ करना चहेन्गे
If it doesn't fit on the screen anymore, it's time to do some organization.
अगर आपका वर्कशीट स्क्रीन में फिट नही हो रहा तो इसका मतलब है की आपको थोडा संगठन करना चाहिए
So let's scroll back to the first columns and these
तो अभी हम फिर से पहले कॉलम पे जाते हैं और
first 5 columns, they have a special role, right?
देखते हैं पहले 5 कॉलम्स को, यह कॉलम्स का एक मुख्या  भूमिका  है, हैं ना?
They are imported from the web. So we can indicate that to future users of the
यह वेब से लिया था. इसीलिए हमे इसे उपयोग करने वाले लोगो को बताना चाहिए
worksheet by
वर्कशीट मे
adding a column here, a border on the side
एक कॉलम जोड़ के , जो एक सीमा है
of the column. And here are two other columns that play a different role,
उस कॉलम का | अभी इधर 2 और कॉलम्स है जिनका अलग भूमिका है
because they are built
क्यूंकी यह बनाया गया है
on the web data and then I have two more columns. And
वेब से लिए हुए डेटा से और मेरे पास अभी 2 और कॉलम्स है
if I've done this, I don't really need the original values anymore,
पर अभी यह करने के बाद मुझे पहले दो असली मूल्यों की ज़रूरत नही है
because with my String operation I have retrieved the information that I need,
क्यूंकी मेरे स्ट्रिंग ऑपरेशन के वजह से वो जानकारी निकली है जो मुझे चाहिए
and I can still refresh the data even though the columns are hidden,
और मैं अभी भी डेटा रेफ्रेश कर सकती भले ही वो कॉलम्स छुपे हैं
the calculation is still refreshed after I hit the Refresh button.
और मेरे गिनती अभी भी नयी है Refresh बटन दबाने के बाद
So this already looks a lot nicer, now in one
देखिए यह अभी से काफ़ी सॉफ नज़र आता है , और अभी आप
view you can see what's going on. Only the final column is bothering me a
देख सकते हैं क्या हो रहा है | पर अभी भी मुझे आखरी कॉलम परेशन कर रहा है
little bit,
थोडा सा
because some of the values have 2 and others have 1 decimal.
क्यूंकी थोड़े मूल्यों के 2 दशमावल है और थोड़े के बस 1
So what we can do here, in this cell formatting
तो अभी हम इधर क्या कर सकते हैं वो है की, सेल फॉरमॅटिंग में
pop-up that you bring up by hitting Ctrl + 1,
जिसे हम पा सकते हैं ctrl + 1 दबाके
we can set the number of decimals. But we can go further than
हम लोग दशमवाल को ठीक कर सकते हैं | पर हम इससे भी आगे जा  सकते हैं
that, we can even indicate that the value is a currency
हम बता सकते हैं की जो यह मूल्या हैं वो मुद्रा है
and add the Euro symbol before it. So it's a lot more clear for someone who's
और हम यूरो का चिन्ह जोड़ेंगे | ताकि यह बाकी लोगों को भी पता चल जाए
going to work with this spreadsheet,
जो आगे इस वर्कशीट पे काम करेंगे
and you remember from the first video that there are probably
और आपको याद होगा पहले वीडियो से की सामानया तोर पे
12 people over the next 5 years. It's a lot clearer for them
12 लोग काम करेंगे इस पे अगले 5 साल तक | यह अभी काफ़ी सॉफ है उन लोगो के लिए
what this value means, because they can see
की इस मूल्या का क्या मतलब है, क्यूंकी वो लोग देख सकते हैं
this is money that we're talking about.
की यह पैसा है जिसके बारे में हम बात कर रहे हैं |
So, organize your spreadsheet well - if you have people over to your house,
इसीलिए अपने स्प्रेअधसीट को संगठन करना चाहिए , अगर लोग आ रहे हैं आपके घर
you're going to clean your house. If people are going to look at your
तो आप ज़रूर सॉफ करेंगे अपना घर | अगर लोग आपके स्प्रेडशीट को देखेंगे तो आप
spreadsheet, you organize your worksheet.
अपना स्प्रेडशीट संगठन करेंगे |
And in the spreadsheet that you're going to send in for the homework,
और जो स्प्रेडशीट आप मुझे भेजने वाले हैं होमवर्क में
we are going to look at your spreadsheet or you are going to
हम देखेंगे आपके स्प्रेडशीट को या आप अपने
peer review
सहयोगी
other people's spreadsheets and this is one of the things that we will be paying
का स्प्रेडशीट देखेंगे और यह एक चीज़ है जो हम ध्यान से
attention to
देखेंगे
in those reviews.
उन समीक्षा में |